Software development is changing
rapidly. How we do things now is not how
we used to do things. AI has changed the
game, but so is the economy and other
outside factors. So, what skills matter
in 2026? Should you go into C
development at all? If you're already in
C development and you're looking for a
job, what should you be doing? In this
video, I'm going to lay out the big
picture steps that you should take to
adjust to software development in 2026.
We're going to start with a reality
check about what it takes to be a
software developer and then we'll get
into what your goal should be, what
technologies you should know, and
finally, how to advance your career in
2026.
Whether you are considering software
development or you have been doing it
for the past 30 years, this video is for
you. So let's get started. And to start
off, we're going to talk about a reality
check. I think this is important. And to
start off with for the things that are
changing for developers. Number one is
that jobs are hard to get now. Does not
mean they're it's impossible to get the
jobs. It does not mean that it's overly
difficult, but it is difficult. And yes,
you may have to struggle for 6 months or
a year or more sometimes to get a job in
the field. Now, there are ways to
shorten that. There are ways to make
sure that you don't hit into that group,
but there are things going to happen to
you where you're going to struggle to
find a job sometimes. And that's
because, you know, there is more
competition. The competition is higher.
These two things go hand inand for a
couple of reasons. back in the early
COVID um era, you know, back in what
2020 or so, uh 2021, um companies were
hiring lots of developers. And so there
became this mindset that if you just had
a decent resume, if you just had a few
buzzwords on your resume, that you could
get hired somewhere and that it wasn't
that hard to get a job. But that wasn't
reality. That's not how software
development has been in the past, nor is
it how it is now. The COVID era of
wildly hiring for jobs and companies
competing for developers is over. And
so, we're back to more of what it is
normally for software development.
Competition is high and yes, jobs can be
harder to get. Now, the reason
competition is high is because this is a
very easy field to get into. I'm not
saying it's a very easy field to do well
in, but it's very easy to say, "Oh, I've
watched a few tutorials. I've gone
through a couple of courses online and
now I must be a software developer. So,
I put that in my resume." And you're
compete against those types of people.
So, you have to figure out how to go
beyond just that. But this is the change
in reality for software developers. Some
of whom are not used to the fact that
yes uh times have changed from that easy
hiring uh place that we were at.
Uh number three uh AI is confusing
companies and what I mean by this is
there is to an extent the idea that that
companies are saying hey I could
probably do more with less which is
always the mantra of companies it does
not matter if it's AI or offshoring or
outsourcing or you know freelance hiring
or whatever the case may be companies
want to do more with less which if you
take a step back and think about it It's
understandable because of the fact that
we do the same thing when you're looking
to buy a new car. You shop around at
different dealerships and say, "Hey, who
has the lowest price for the same
value?" That's what you're looking for.
Well, in the same way, that's what
companies are looking for. They want
more money in their own pockets and less
money going to their employees. And so,
they're always going to figure out how
to do more with less. So there's been an
awful lot of talk from very large
companies including Microsoft and OpenAI
and and Meta and others that are saying
we're going to replace software
developers or we're going to greatly
reduce the need for software developers
with our AI products. Now
you have to remember that they're trying
to sell a product, right? They're trying
to sell their own thing and try and get
companies on board with them. But that's
what they're pushing. uh Microsoft is
really pushing hard for every developer
needs to be using AI to go faster and
farther and it's a bit unrealistic. But
companies that are not those big
companies, they're a bit more confused
because if they say, "Oh, well, this is
what the market leaders are doing,
therefore we must do it, too." And so
there are companies that are trying
they're trying to hire less developers
or even lay off developers sometimes. um
where they are expecting the AI to do
the work of the developers and this
doesn't go well. It has not gone well.
There has not been a company that you
know does this long term and goes yes
that was a great decision. I mean maybe
it's a tiny little company that do that
but not any large scale company. So what
happens instead is we see over and over
again companies are hiring back those
people and so they are bringing those
developers back in or they're they're
you know trying to do other things to
pretend like the AI is still working
like outsourcing development to to cover
their shortfalls and so on. So this is
causing a lot of confusion in the
industry. Some companies may be laying
off because of AI. Other companies may
be hiring because of AI. Some companies
are looking at AI as rightfully the
ability for it to to launch them forward
faster. And so they're saying, "Hey, you
know what? Let's just empower our
developers and be able to do more with
these tools. So instead of saying let's
pay less, instead of saying let's just
produce more or let's, you know, take on
more projects, etc." And so there are
opportunities at those companies or
maybe you know there's a little bit of
movement either way but it's causing a
lot of confusion in the job market a lot
of turmoil and so that is causing some
problems when it comes to hiring versus
not. It's changing who is hiring and
who's not. Number four vibe coding looks
great. Um, it there's an awful lot of
people out there, an awful lot of
companies, awful lot of people promoting
the idea that vibe coding works. And no,
it doesn't. Not in the way that most
people think it does. So, there's this
idea that, hey, you don't have to be a
developer. You can just vibe code an app
and it will be great. And that's not how
that works. It repeatedly is proven
that's not how that works. And if you
look the people who create Vibe Code
apps that actually work, that are
actually secure, that are actually
performant, that actually can be
maintained long-term,
those are the people who are already
highly skilled developers.
So they're not really vibe coding in the
way that they're promoting it or way a
lot of people are promoting it, which is
you don't have to know the topic. You
just have to tell the AI to do its thing
and it does. So over and over again,
it's been proven that when you just let
the AI do its thing, it's probably 80%
right. And then that 20% is an unsecure
mess and it creates bad code that's hard
to maintain. So it's not like, well,
it's good enough. And I've heard that
argument, it's good enough. It's not
good enough because security isn't a
good enough thing. your data retention
isn't a good enough thing. Your
assurance that your data is not going to
get mixed up with someone else's data is
not a good enough thing. And so letting
an AI just go crazy on that, that's not
a good thing. But when it comes to again
looking at how companies are looking at
looking at how people who are coming
into software development are looking at
it, vibe coding looks on the outside.
It's got a pretty skin. It's got a
pretty look to it and so it looks like
that developers aren't need anymore and
that causes even more confusion. So
there are things we acknowledge in that
and the fact that yes that is causing
some market turmoil but that doesn't
mean that it's the right thing or the
long-term solution for software
development. So let's talk about the
actual reality. So we talked about the
the changes for developers, but let's
talk the actual reality. Reality number
one is software development pays well.
This is a thing that people overlook or
they they discount. I hear a lot of
people say, "Oh, it's it's not a good
time to be a software developer. Go do
something else, anything else." So I did
this uh this uh thought experiment with
a person on YouTube recently where they
were saying, "Hey, you know, software
development is not a field you want to
get into. Go anywhere else.
And it is a field that is going to take
work to get into. We'll talk about that.
But I said, let's just look at any other
field. Let's take electrician. We're
going to use US numbers. And I used the
US median income means the middle
income. So half of the people who are
electricians make less than this. Half
make more than this. And I did a thought
experiment where I said, "What if you
got hired tomorrow as an electrician?"
It's not going to happen. and you have
to have training and all the rest. But
let's just say you did and you worked
for 10 years.
How long would you have to work as a
software developer at the same software
development median income in order to
meet or eclipse the same income as an
electrician. You had to work for less
than five years. So you could be
unemployed with zero dollars coming in
for five years and still make out better
in the end being a software developer
than you could an electrician. That's
nothing bad against electricians. If you
want to be an electrician, you're good
at it, do it, please. We need
electricians. And you can figure out
ways to hopefully make more money than
that. But the point is that software
development pays well. And so it's worth
some of this extra pain and difficulty
that comes with the hard work of getting
into this field because it is going to
be hard work. So when you're looking at
well don't do that, compare it. Be
honest about what your alternatives are.
Not everyone should be a software
developer, but if that is a field you
want to go into, you can do very well.
So the actual reality is software
development pays well. The alternatives
are almost entirely worse. Now worse in
terms of money, okay? And that's not the
only way you should evaluate a career.
Please don't evaluate a career just
based upon money. But you need to be
honest about your evaluations. If your
bent, if your drive is to be a software
developer, it is a great career to get
into. If your drive is to be in
healthcare, that's a better place for
you to be probably because that's what
you're going to be more happy and more
fulfilled doing. So, we're just talking
right now about dollars and cents
income. So too often I hear people say
don't do software development and their
idea behind it is it's hard. It takes a
lot of work. It's it's hard to get a
job. These are all things that are true.
But what's your alternative? What are
you suggesting that they do instead?
Because it's not enough to say don't do
something because that's doesn't provide
any value. It just provides a negative
output. Instead, say these are the
things that are probably better and back
that up with actual data, not just
anecdotal. Well, my neighbor's friend's
buddy had is, you know, making lots of
money doing this. That's just anecdotal
evidence. Look at it from the actual
monetary standpoint. Software
development, the career is growing more
rapidly than almost any other career in
the US.
It makes more than almost any other
career in the US, especially for the
fact that it does not require even a
degree. Yes, sometimes a degree can be
helpful, but that doesn't mean it's
required. So, it's easier to get into
and it pays a whole lot better, which is
also why there's so much competition,
which does make it more difficult. Okay.
Number three, AI will drive job growth.
And this is something that people don't
realize or don't don't see as a a
possibility sometimes because of the
fact that they're locked in on the idea
that AI is going to replace developers.
And it's not. We have seen, we have
proven year after year, we've been told,
well, in the next version, in the next
version, in the next version, it will
somehow get better. It'll get better.
It'll get better. And it hasn't. Yes,
there have been advances in AI and yes,
the LLMs that are are putting out code
are doing a better job for the most part
than they were in previous versions. But
we what we're seeing is a small
incremental change now as opposed to
this grand massive difference in how
things work. So software developers
aren't getting replaced. Instead, what's
going to happen is it is going to make
it easier for more companies to hire
less developers and still have custom
development. So, think of it this way.
Back in the the 70s and early 80s, kind
of before I was into into computers,
well, computers were basically these big
mainframes and only, you know, bigger
companies owned these. And so your your
average mom and pop shop that maybe was
a dry cleaner or a you know a laundromat
or something else they didn't own a
computer because it didn't make
financial sense. So we only had a few
computers relatively and then the
computer got cheaper and faster and all
of a sudden more and more businesses
owned a computer. they they could afford
it and because of that more and more
businesses use software which also gave
rise to the software developer. The same
thing is true here with AI is that it's
going to make it easier and easier for
smaller and smaller companies to invest
a little bit and get some value out of
it. So it's going to drive job growth.
If AI succeeds, it will drive job
growth. If it fails,
it's going to drive job growth because
we're gonna have to fill in the gaps
here. So either way, software
development is going to grow. We're
going to have more need for more
software developers.
And this final point in or one of the
final points in this actual reality is
there is no easy path.
This is something that too often people
get sold on a dream. Um, and I get, you
know, push back from people sometimes.
They say, "Well, the reason that you say
the things you do or the reason you push
people a certain way is because you sell
courses and that must mean that you're,
you know, biased and you're trying to
just sell courses." That's not the case.
I understand why you would question
that. You should question that, but
that's not why I do what I do. Um but
too often people been sold that bill of
goods that hey if you just watch this
course it will you know make your life
better because you will be a software
developer and you can um you know do
these things and if you look at how I
sell let's say my C# master course which
is kind of my my cornerstone course uh
all my master courses are um but when I
sell my C# master course I say that you
can walk into it knowing nothing about C
and when you walk out. You can be a
junior or even mid-level C developer,
but there's a difference here. It
depends on the effort you put in during
the course. If you just watch the
videos, you're not even qualified to be
a junior developer. You're just not
because I'm going to encourage you over
and over and over throughout that course
to build this. Hey, do this homework.
And I have people push back and say,
"Where's the answers to the homework?"
And I said, "No, you have to evaluate
the answer. You have to figure it out.
I've given you all the tools. Now you
build something." Because what happens
in your job is that you're given a task.
You're not given the answer. You have to
figure out how to make that work and how
to figure out if it matches the
requirements. So that's the difference
is that it does take work. It takes a
lot of work. And so when I say, hey, if
you're going to watch an hour of of
lecture, you need to spend about two to
five hours
actually doing the work building
applications to test out what you just
learned. So it's going to take you two
to five times the number of hours of the
course in total work to actually get to
the point of being a junior or even
mid-level developer. It's not about
learning syntax. There's a lot more to
it. You have to put in the work. There
is no easy path. And this comes back to
what the the lie that AI is selling and
a lot of people are buying is that AI is
the shortcut. Hey, let's take a shortcut
to learning software development by just
having the AI do it for us. Well, that
is super dangerous because what I see
already happening is that people don't
know how to be a developer outside of
just telling the AI, "Hey, do this and
then watching it do it." The problem is
the AI is wrong way too often. And they
don't know it because they're not a
developer themselves. They're just a
supervisor of an AI who has less and
less skill and actually telling the AI,
"No, you're wrong because they have less
and less insight into that. They don't
know what's going on."
So, there is no easy path. And if you
try and shortcut, if you try and take
the the the quicker way that is, you
know, have AI do it or have AI help you,
well then what's going to happen is
you're going to stunt your growth and
you're going to find out that there
isn't a place in software development
for you. You won't be able to find a job
very easily, if at all, because you're
not actually that valuable because you
add nothing to the process. You're just
prompting with AI, and that's not
useful. Anyone can do that. So, finally,
this isn't for everyone. I've said
before, and people get confused when I
say it, but I've said before that anyone
can learn software development. Anyone
can be a software developer. And people
push back on that a lot. And the reason
why is they think that it's somehow, you
know, super hard to do or they they hold
the magical keys for being a developer
themselves. But the reality is anyone
can do this, but it isn't for everyone.
There's a difference there. So, anyone
can push hard and do this. It's going to
take work. It's going to take struggle.
It's going to take effort and pushing
through the hard things because being a
developer really, that's kind of the the
secret is that we're always struggling,
right? It's not, did you have a hard day
working through problems? Because that's
just a normal Tuesday. That's that's
what we do. That's our job. And the
majority of our job is debugging
problems and figuring out why things
don't work when they expect them to. So,
this is a job that's going to be
frustrating. And for some people, that's
energizing. For some people, finding the
the solution and and figure out
[clears throat] how to write that code
that that solves a problem is
lifegiving.
And for some people, it's just draining.
And so this isn't for everyone. So you
do need to evaluate if is this for me.
If if you're just looking at software
development as the easy way to get a
quick buck or to become somehow rich by
being a software developer, this might
not be for you because that's not what's
going to sustain you. Now, if you're
willing to put the hard work in, then
yeah, you could, but it's not for
everyone. Okay, so that's the reality.
Let's talk the keys to success as a
software developer. Number one, don't
take shortcuts. Just don't take
shortcuts. AI is a big shortcut. Um, and
that's something that we'll talk more
about as we go through, but but don't
use AI as a shortcut. Don't use AI
instead of learning. Don't use AI
instead of building things yourself or
writing the code yourself. Um, so don't
take those shortcuts, but there's other
shortcuts as well. Um, you know, it used
to be that you would spend a lot of time
building applications and now people
really push back and they really don't
want to build applications. They say,
well, I don't want to spend a time or it
takes so long. And yes, it does and it's
hard work and it's going to take
discipline. But you know what? That's
how you stand out from the crowd is that
you do the things others won't. Don't
take the shortcuts and just say, "Well,
I'll just vibe code it and call it
good." You didn't learn anything there.
It It's like in a classroom. When I was
in high school, I got straight A's. It
was super easy for me. And so, I never
learned how to study. And so, when I got
to college, that didn't translate so
well. I remember my my freshman class, I
took calculus one. The very first thing
that happened was I failed calculus one
because I didn't know how to study. I
didn't know how to put the effort in
beyond just listening to a lecture and
regurgitating it onto the page. And
that's not how college works, especially
not that class. So that's when I I
learned that I have to learn how to do
the work. I had to learn how to not just
watch something and then regurgitate it,
which is what some people do with
videos. They just watch it and expect to
then know it. That's not how that works.
What you have to do is you have to
figure out what are the ways to to get
this information to stick in my brain
and how do I get the experience in these
areas in order to really grasp the
concepts. So for me in calculus, one of
the things was I had to take notes. And
I found that typing notes wasn't going
to work because when I did, I focused
too much on formatting and should I do
bullet points here and how I put a
diagram over here? I can't really. So I
spent too much time formatting. Instead,
I learned was get out a piece of paper
and a pen and write things down.
Sometimes
just the very act of writing it down
would help solidify things in my brain.
But then I'd also take those notes and
practice. I would do my homework which
wasn't wasn't graded. And so before I
didn't do my homework because why do
something that's not graded? Well, I
figured out why because it's the
practice. It's the idea of doing this
over and over so it becomes muscle
memory. And so I learned that I couldn't
take shortcuts to success. I had to take
the long road because that's how I
became an A student in calculus is by
not [clears throat] taking the shortcuts
but taking the long road doing the
things that are hard and frustrating and
quite frankly I didn't want to do. take
notes and spend time outside of class
working on this and practicing this and
doing problems over and over again until
I figured out how it worked and I was
able to commit that into my muscle
memory. So, don't take shortcuts in
software development.
Don't let AI lead.
This is the really the dividing line
between you're in serious trouble as a
developer and you are going to do well
as a developer and that is does AI lead
or not because if you allow AI to lead
what happens is more and more you will
just be signing off on what AI does.
When AI gives you 500 lines of new C
code that it's written, how well do you
actually review that code, do you
refactor it? Do you evaluate the
security of it? Do you evaluate the does
it fit into the overall hole? Or do you
go, hey, it works? Because the more you
lean towards, hey, it works, the more
you lean towards just rubber stamping
what the AI does, the less value you are
as a developer. because quite frankly
there's probably people that can explain
the problems better than you can and so
that's all you're doing at that point is
explaining the problems to the AI.
You're not actually evaluating if the AI
fulfilled the solution to the problems.
So that's an important thing is that
dividing line don't let AI lead. Uh also
put in the hard work. This comes back to
number one. No shortcuts but put in the
hard work. Make sure that you are
spending the time because this is how
you stand out from the crowd. If you put
in the hard work, that's something that
the vast majority developers will not
do. And in fact, there's probably people
watching this video right now, I know
people watching this video right now,
they're going, "Yeah, it's just too
hard. I don't want to do that. It takes
up too much of my time. I don't want to
spend my off hours working on on
software development." Guess what? You
want to be a person that goes beyond
that person so you can stand out from
everybody else. So put in the hard work.
Also do what others will not do.
There are some things that people who
are in development just don't want to do
and they're going to push it off on
anybody else. And the the problem there
is that while that may work, what's
going to happen is they become less and
less valuable compared to the person who
does what others will not. A prime
example of this is if you go to a u a
database developer conference which I
have done I've spoken at um developer
conferences for for database development
and you talk to the people and a lot of
database developers will say that
they're actually a software developer
first and they became the database
developer or they're an accidental DBA.
That's the a pretty common term you'll
hear a lot. And the reason for that is
because first of all, they knew
something about databases. And so they
were using that knowledge at work to aid
in their job beyond the just software
developer role, but also they were
willing to take that on. And because of
that, they became even more valuable to
their organization. They did what others
would not. That's just one example out
of many. There's also people who figure
out how to make automation and DevOps
work. There are people who figure out
how to improve performance in cloud
while reducing costs. There are people
who figure out how to use containers to
make applications easier to work with
locally. There's people that, you know,
that figure out these other things,
these other areas that are at the edges
of software development and because of
that become more valuable to their
organization. do what others will not.
And finally, continual growth. This is a
big key to success. Too often I see
developers who stagnate in their role.
They think that, well, I'm getting
better at at doing our internal system.
That's that's great in a in a sense, but
here's the thing. You might not have
that job forever. Your company might not
be around forever. Your role might not
be around forever. And what happens when
you lose that role or want to leave that
role or get frustrated with the new
management in the new direction? You're
behind the curve because you stopped
growing and it's really hard to pick up
especially when other people have been
keeping up this entire time and so they
launch way ahead of you just by putting
in the continual work. It's, you know,
you don't take a a break during a
marathon. You don't stop at mile five
and just go, you know what, I'm going to
hang out here for a while because it's
really hard to then place in the top 10
of that marathon because everyone else
has been making consistent progress
throughout the race where you're sitting
down and just hanging out. So continual
growth is the final key of success for
software development. Let's talk about
the bottom line here. The bottom line is
that software development takes hard
work. It takes determination to push
through the hard parts, which not
everyone can do. If you're not willing
to do that, this career probably isn't
for you. So, you know what? It's there's
no shame in saying this isn't my career.
This is what I want to do. That's
totally fine. Now, for the rest of you,
I would encourage you to look at this
the other way. Is that you know what,
I'm going to put in the hard work. I'm
going to have determination. I'm going
to push through because this is the
career for me. I'm willing to do that,
but I'm willing to put up with the the
work that a job really is in order to
get the rewards that I'm looking forward
to. Now, let's jump into goals for
software developers and different
levels. So, we'll talk first about new
developers. If you're thinking about
being a software developer or you're
just getting started in software
development, um these are some goals you
should have. Number one, uh we're
talking specifically for C here, but
learn C beyond the syntax. Too often
people think when they first get into
software development that when you know
more syntax, you must be a senior
developer. That is not it at all. Um a
junior developer might know almost every
bit of syntax in C#. So that's not what
makes you a a senior developer. So go
beyond just being a C developer and then
don't rely on AI tooling. So what you're
going to do is you're going to start
building things. Start learning how to
actually build applications. Too often I
see people who say, "Oh, well I know C#
really well." And I ask, "Well, have you
built an application?" Well, no. I
haven't built an application. I just
don't have time. it's a lot of work and
it's I don't have the right idea or
whatever. No, learn how to build things
because that's what a software developer
does. So, and then with that, don't rely
on AI tooling. Don't rely on it at all.
In fact, if you're learning software
development, uninstall the AI tools,
disable them, don't use them. Because
what's going to do if you start using
them is it's going to be a crutch to
kind of fill in the gaps. You think, but
what's actually happening is it's
creating gaps. It's allow you to
continue when in fact you have gaps and
you don't even realize because it works.
And so what happens is that when you go
to actually build something without an
AI tool, you figure out I can't build
that. I don't know how to build that.
I've I'm missing so much stuff because
you allowed gaps into your knowledge. So
don't do that. Just turn it off. It's
not the right time for you later. That's
fine. And you're not going to miss
anything. You're not going to be
stunted. You're not going to be behind
the curve because you haven't learned AI
tools yet. Learn the actual language
first. Learn how to build in it. Learn
well beyond the syntax of it.
Build real things. Build real things
without AI. Learn how to work with this
so that you know how to actually use the
language. You know how things work. You
know how things are architected. You
know how things fit together. You know
the questions to ask. when you do
eventually not now but eventually start
using AI tooling you know the questions
to ask to say hey I don't think that's
right or hey what about the security
there what about the the data protection
there what about crosscontamination
between two different companies in our
database these are really important
questions to know how to ask and the
only way you'll know how to ask them
well is if you've actually built things.
It's not if you've read enough books.
It's have you actually got practical
handson knowledge. I if you're going to
go to a surgeon and you need to have
your leg operated on, you don't want to
go to a surgeon who says, "Yes, I've
I've watched all the tutorials. I've
read all the books about this. I'm sure
I can do this." That's not who you want.
Who you want is a person who says, "I've
done this a hundred times. Not a
problem. This is what we're going to do.
I had that happen with my wisdom teeth.
So, I was older and still had my wisdom
teeth, but they were causing problems.
And so, I went to a a surgeon who's
going to take my wisdom teeth out. And
he did not have a whole lot of um
confidence in his own technique because
the fact he said, "Oh, well, you're
older and this could happen." I mean, he
was giving some really scary things
about how I might, you know, lose uh or
might hit a nerve in my jaw. I might not
be able to, you know, smile correctly
ever ever since. I might cause problems
where I might break my jaw. All these
things might happen because he had not
done this procedure on a person of my
age
almost ever. It was a very rare thing
for him to do. And so I went, you know
what, no, not going to do that. But then
I went to a different surgeon and he
said, "First of all, I've done this a
number of times. People your age, not a
problem. Here's what I do and why." And
he had a whole bunch of research. He
done a whole bunch of learning. So he
could quote articles and quote uh
statistics and he could, you know, point
me to the journals where it talks about
how to do this and why I do this and
what the outcomes are and so on. But he
also had a whole bunch of hands-on
experience of having done it. Guess
what? I felt very confident. When it
comes to companies hiring developers,
they don't want the first person. They
want the second person. They don't want
a person who says, "Yeah, I've watched a
ton of tutorials. I've, you know, I I've
seen this done a number of times." What
they want is a person that says, "Yeah,
I've done a bunch of research. I know
how this work and why this works and how
to do this, but I've also built a number
of things."
that's what you want to be because
that's what employers are looking for.
So for new developers, those are my top
three things for your goals. Now for job
seekers, maybe you've already been a
software developer for a bit or maybe
you're just starting off off looking for
a job. You now have the qualifications
you'd think to be a software developer.
Either way, if you're looking for a job,
here are some goals for you. Stand out
from the crowd.
Too often I have people argue with me
and say,"Well, I don't want to do that.
That's a whole lot of work." Or, "I
don't want to, you know, put in that
extra effort." And so what they tell me
is, "I'm going to do the same exact
thing as every other job seeker out
there, but I'm going to expect different
results."
Does that sound logical to you? If the
job market is full of developers looking
for jobs, and there's a lot of
developers looking for jobs right now,
and if the job market isn't booming like
it was 5 years ago, and it's not, even
though there's still jobs there, it's
just not nearly as as uh you know, empty
as it used to be. Well, if there's less
job openings and lots of people looking
for jobs, you can't do the same thing as
everybody else and expect different
results. You have to figure out how to
be the person that stands out from the
crowd from the get-go. That means
standing out just with your resume.
Standing out the very first time you
interview, standing out when you do a
technical interview. You need to stand
out when you talk to an employer. These
are all things that you need to figure
out how to do to stand out from the
crowd. That means doing things that
other people are not doing. This does
not mean wacky shenanigans. This does
not mean making your resume into this
multicolored clown themed, you know,
thing where you open up the piece of
paper and balloons fly out. That is not
what I'm talking about. What I'm talking
about is ways to show off that you are a
better developer, that you are more
experienced, that you can do more, you
can offer more to the company than
anybody else who is applying.
Number two, show off what you can do.
This is one way to stand out is to show
off what you can do. And that means you
have to have built something. That's
that's what you're doing already, right?
like these are things you need to do.
Number three, make connections.
We'll talk more about this, but as a
software developer, yes, it's important
that you make connections
because that will make your job seeking
ability easier. It will make that
process quicker. It will give you more
opportunities to move up and move around
in software development because of the
fact it's who you know now. You don't
have to know anybody in order to become
a software developer and get hired, but
it makes it a whole lot easier.
And so, yeah, statistically,
generally speaking, software developers
are introverts. That's kind of how you
know what type of person is attracted to
this field. People who expect that
they're going to keep their head down
and just work on their computer and no
one's going to talk to them. That's not
really how the job works, but that's the
expectation and that's what a lot of
software developers are is introverts.
I'm not saying everybody is, but you
need to figure out how to overcome that.
I'm an introvert. That's at my core.
That's who I am. I have learned through
hard work how to make connections. So,
working to, you know, connect with
people, it's really hard, but you need
to put the effort in in order to make
those connections because that will make
your life easier. So, work to make those
connections.
Uh, practice interviewing. That's really
important. Practice interviewing.
interview with a person who knows
nothing about software development
because guess what? Your first interview
will probably be with a person who knows
nothing about software development.
So give your friend who has no clue or
your your spouse or your your brother or
sister, your parent, give them the job
description and your resume and say,
"Can you interview me for this role?"
And then have them ask questions. And
they're going to ask bad questions.
Guess what? So is HR. and then ask them,
"How do I come across? Do you think I I
meet these expectations? What do you
think I could do better to meet these
expectations more?" And they're going to
say things that you're going to want to
push back against. For example, they may
say, "Well, this role is for a .NET
developer." And you say you're a C#
developer. I don't I don't see how that
aligns. And you might go, "Oh my
goodness, C isnet." Don't get angry
because that's exactly what's going the
HR person is going to say. Only they're
not going to say it to you. They're
going to think that as they put you
through a filter. So, learn how to make
adjustments based upon that. Learn from
those experiences.
Do practice interviews where you do
technical interviews. I did a whole
course on this. This is not a well it's
kind of a plug but um I did a course on
this where I did gave you a 100
questions and allowed you to take the
time to answer five questions at a time
20 times where I gave you five questions
and I give you five answers that I would
answer like but that gives you the
opportunity to practice the interview
process but I think it's important
you'll notice that the courses that I do
I feel are really important for software
developers
I'm not here to try to, you know, trick
you into doing things that are not good
for you. I'm here to give you the tools
necessary to do the things that you need
to in order to become a better software
developer. That's why I have so many
courses that are building real
applications. I have courses that are,
you know, let's dive deep into beyond
just the syntax of C or web development
because I want you to know more. I want
you to become a better developer. And
part of this is practicing every part of
the process from when you first learn
the first bit of C# syntax all the way
through practicing your interviewing.
So [snorts]
next up, customize your resume. Again,
going back to that first point, stand
out from the crowd. Too often people
turn in generic résumés to hundreds of
jobs and go, "Man, nobody's hired
because nobody even contacted me." Guess
what? If they didn't contact you, your
resume wasn't good enough. Now, it may
be that you don't have the skills
necessary for that job. That may be, but
more likely it's the fact that you did
not put in a good enough job on making
your resume fit the job that you're
applying to. Make it easy for them to
say yes.
Okay? When you just give a generic
resume and say, "Well, it's just too
hard to customize." Yep. And you know
what? You're not going to have a job
because you're not going to get the
interviews. If you're going through a
100 plus applications and getting one or
less interviews,
it's probably on you. I I'm sorry that's
harsh. It's direct, but it's probably on
you because
this is not a matter of, oh, they're
fake jobs. Most likely not. Most likely
not. Um the fake jobs, they're trying to
scam you in some way. These aren't
scams. When it's on Indeed, it's not a
scam. what they're trying to do is
trying to find the best people for the
job and your resume isn't matching that.
I know because I've read thousands of
them and I can tell you that when I've
had thousands of résumés for one job
that the vast majority of them were
easily rejected in round one before I
even talked to the person because they
had no match to what I was saying this
is what I'm looking for.
So figure out how to make your resume
match because you can't expect an
employer to talk to every person or
evaluate in depth every particular
person and tease the information out of
you. That's not how it works. You need
to stand out from the crowd. So
customize your resume. So those are the
goals for job seekers. Let's talk about
current developers. Maybe you're in a
role you're like, you know what, I'm
set. I got a job. I can probably skip
this whole thing. No, you can't. Don't
skip this. So here's your goals
supplement with AI. This is where I
first would say that AI can be valuable
is when you're in a current role when
you are skilled. You're not a junior
developer anymore. Maybe you're a
midlevel or hopefully more towards
senior developer. Supplement your
development with AI. Again, don't let it
lead, but supplement your development
with AI. It can be really valuable.
Number two, continue to grow. And that
doesn't mean let the AI teach you. What
it means is continue to add new skills,
continue to practice and go back to the
basics. Again, don't let AI be anywhere
involved in the growth process because
it can leave gaps. It will leave gaps.
It will leave you a bad understanding of
a topic. Even though it looks great and
maybe 95% of what it will teach you
would be great, that 5% oo there's some
bad gaps there that can cause some
serious problems that make it almost not
worth it to learn it at all. So get AI
out of the process. Continue to grow in
new areas.
Put in the hard work.
It's going to take some hard work.
You're going to have to probably work
outside of your nto-five job. And I know
people don't love to do that. But here's
the deal. Is your career important?
Because this field is hard. This field
is not just a bed of roses where if you
just put in your time and punch the time
clock that they will somehow give you
magically lots of money. That's not how
it works. Companies are always looking
for more. And so if you don't put the
work in, you're going to find that you
are unemployed. I know a lot of people
who are senior developers or say they
are who don't have a job and they're
struggling to get the next job because
they got laid off and all of a sudden
now they don't have the skills necessary
for the current market and they're
struggling struggling because they don't
they have not kept up. They didn't put
the hard work in. Now they're faced with
either I do a lot of hard work or I
don't get a job. And even when I do the
hard work, it's kind I sat down at that
five mile marker in the in the marathon.
There's a lot of people ahead of me. So,
put in the hard work even in your
current role and prepare for a change.
Your job may not be there forever.
In fact, most jobs probably won't be
there forever. It doesn't matter if you
work for a huge company or a tiny little
company. Your job probably won't be
there forever. So, those are your goals
as a current developer.
Let's talk now about technology and what
technologies you should know. So whether
you're a brand new developer or you're a
seasoned senior developer, these are
things you should know and maybe you'll
find yourself on different parts of this
spectrum. So first let's talk about the
language and primarily we're going to
talk C here. So um this is all about net
but specifically C.
LearnNet 6 through 10. Okay, you don't
have to know every net, but you should
be comfortable working not just in the
cutting edge but in older versions of
net as well. So just spin up older
projects, make sure you know how to
navigate them and how to work with them
because not every company is going to
upgrade to the latest cuttingedge
version of net. I highly encourage if
you're on net to be on net 10, but not
every company will do that. Also learn
net framework. I know you may not want
to and you may say, I I'm not going to
work on .NET Framework, so I'm not going
to even worry about it. You are limiting
your career. That's just how it is
because there's a lot of companies out
there that are working on .NET
Framework. There's a lot of companies
out there that are using Windforms in
.NET Framework and Web Forms as well.
Guess what? Those aren't fun frameworks,
but you know what? That gets you a foot
in the door. It gets you experience and
it allows you to be the hero in that
company where you can start moving them
migrating them towards .NET 10 and
beyond. So
learn net framework,
learn how to work with APIs. That's the
web is increasingly valuable. We're
increasingly connected with every
application we build. And so knowing how
to build an API is important. And part
of that has to do with the fact that if
you have an API, you can connect it to
other services, including AIS, and
that's going to be something that you're
going to have to work with more. And
with that, learn how to integrate AI
into your applications. It's a great
skill to have in your back pocket. Now,
this is not a skill you add if you're a
brand new C# developer, but if you're a
mid-level or above developer, yeah,
learn how to embed a AI into your app,
your C# application. I did a whole
course on this. Again, I do courses to
help you meet the needs of today. So,
learn how to integrate an AI into your
application. You may not love it. You
may not think that it's valuable. And
for the most part, I do think there is
limited value in integrating AI into an
application. But what are you trying to
do? Are you trying to make a moral stand
or a a stand about, you know, what is
right? [snorts]
Or are you trying to get a job? Are you
trying to work with an employer? An
employer might say, "We want to do
this." Or you might say, "Well, yeah, I
can I can integrate an AI into a C#
application." And that might be the
added push that a company needs. They
might say, "You know what? We want to do
that at some point." So having a person
on staff that can do that, that'd be
great. All of a sudden, you have put
yourself ahead of your competition.
You're standing out.
Learn ASP.Core. And too many people
don't understand what ASP..NET Core is.
That is API. That's also MVC. That's
also Razer Pages. But it's also Blazer
Web Apps. and Blaze Webb Assembly. All
of those are built on the same core of
ASP.NET Core. So, learn it. Learn how to
use it. Learn how to integrate different
pieces together. Learn how to put a
Blazer Bit into an MVC application
because you may work in a company that
has MBC. They may say, "Well, we want
to, you know, just have a little bit of
client side functionality." Well, you
really don't want to have this whole uh
JavaScript system in place with npm and
all the rest in order to just put a
little client side interactivity on a
form or two. This is where a blazer bit
would be really helpful. You just drop
that in, use the same language, and
you're done. So, learning how those
things interact with each other really
important.
Learn crossplatform.
more and more I think we're going to see
that people are moving away from just
Windows. I mean I think that Windows is
pushing people pretty hard away from
Windows and so learning how to do
cross-platform development with C#
really important. Um you know there's
different ways of doing that. So,
Microsoft has their own with Maui and
you can either use a uh a ZAML syntax or
you can use a blazer syntax and build
for Windows and Mac desktop as well as
iOS and Android or you can use a
third-party tool like Uno or Avalonia
and you can build crossplatform on
Windows and Mac and Linux desktops as
well as iOS and Android and the web. So,
you get to choose which works for you.
Personally, I lean towards Uno a lot
because of the fact that it does deploy
to more platforms and it does have the
complete vertical integration with all
the different tooling that it has. Um,
I've done a video on that. We'll
probably do more videos on that. Um, but
learn crossplatform because it opens up
more possibilities. It makes you more
valuable. That's the whole point here is
to get you to stand out from the crowd.
So when an interviewer says, you know,
you you've worked on C#, so you probably
haven't done much, you know, except for
on Windows. You could say, I actually
built for for Linux desktop before, they
might say, really? Yeah. Yeah, I used
Uno to do that, and this is what I did.
All of a sudden, you stand out. Okay,
learn Aspire. Um, Aspire is a tool from
Microsoft that I've done an intro video.
We'll do more videos on in this coming
year. Um, but it's a tool for helping
you work with these complex applications
locally and learning how to see all the
interactions with with the the tracing
and the the logging and and all these
other things in one place locally. So,
it makes working with complex
applications easier. So I would
encourage you learn it, learn how to
work with it because it will make your
your life easier as a developer, but
it's also going to again help you stand
out in a a crowded marketplace.
Next up, let's talk about supporting
tooling. So DevOps, um, deploying
applications in general, knowing how to
do that. Again, we talked before the
accidental DBA. I think the new term is
probably accidental DevOps engineer. Um
because as developers we kind of know
our way around technology and one of the
areas that's become more and more on the
developers is deploying our
applications. So knowing how to you know
work with GitHub actions or uh work with
other tooling to get your software from
the source code all the way to
production is important. learning how to
do CI/CD, learning how to work with
actions and work with the YAML and
figure out how that all works. It's a
valuable thing to know how to do and it
adds more value.
Uh, number two, containers. Whether you
like them or not, containers are the
future for the cloud. And because of
that, they're also the future for
development in general. In fact, if you
deploy an Azure web app where you say,
"Here's my source code. deploy that to a
web server in Azure. What you're
actually doing is deploying to a
container.
Even if you don't use a containerized
version, it's still container because
that's how the cloud works. And as an
extension, that's how development will
work in general because of the fact that
you're often deploying to the cloud. And
even if you're not deploying to the
cloud, it makes life easier. I've done a
number of videos, a number of different
ways where you can run one line, two
lines, three lines of of code and all of
a sudden you could have a SQL server or
a MongoDB database or you can have a
Reddis cache or whatever else you want
locally running on your machine with
very little work and at the end of it
you can turn it off and it goes away.
Super valuable. Learn how to work with
them. It will add value to your
employer. databases. Too often databases
get overlooked as yeah, we store data
there and people will work really hard
to optimize, you know, their for loops
and optimize, you know, this specific
code and try to figure out how to save,
you know, half a nancond off of working
with this bit of code and they forget
that they're accessing a data from a
database.
That's where the vast majority of your
performance will be won or lost is
talking to your database, getting the
data out. Learn how to let the database
do database work. Too often developers
want to just dump all the data down to
their application and then do filtering
and sorting. That's not efficient.
learn how to let let's say SQL do SQL
work and learn what work SQL should do
on its side versus what work you should
do on your side. Learn how to optimize.
Learn how to secure your data. And
that's not just password security.
That's also making sure you don't
cross-contaminate data, making sure
queries can't access more than they
should, making sure that your connection
strings are locked down, and so many
other things. So learn how to work with
databases and not just one multiple
cloud management. This is a similar
thing here. Learning how to work with a
cloud is going to add a lot of value
because the fact that the cloud can be
wildly expensive for employers, wildly
expensive. Or it can be much much
cheaper than doing it yourself. So learn
how to work with the cloud. Learn how to
manage resources. Learn when the cloud
is the right choice. Learn when it's the
wrong choice. Learn how to optimize your
performance in the cloud as well as your
monetary performance. Learn how to
monitor how much you're spending and so
many other things. Cloud management is
really important because if you come to
your employer and say, "I want to work
with Azure. Let's deploy to Azure." your
employer rightfully is going to say, "E,
that sounds expensive. We we got our our
self-hosting here. It's fine." Um, you
can come back with, "Here is why it's
cheaper." I've done this for companies
where, you know, one company I worked
for, they had uh their servers, it was
actually they were uh renting full
servers from, I believe, Rackspace. Um,
so it was actually somebody else's
server, but they were renting the full
thing, doing the Windows updates
themselves, etc.
We went from that to fully in the cloud
with a redundant zone, with more
resources, with more performance, with
more everything
for a fraction of the cost
because I knew how to make the cloud
work for my employer. Guess what? My
employer was thrilled. And I've done
that multiple times because if you know
what you're doing, you can stand out
from the crowd by providing value and
not just danger and cost and all the
rest.
Learn AI dev tools. Okay. At some point,
and this is not when you're a rookie
developer, this is when you are
solidified as a software developer.
Learn dev tools. Now right now AI
development tools like uh Claude or
Copilot etc. these tools are moving very
very fast and they're constantly
changing u which LLM they're using and
and how they're working and the tooling
and it's it's a moving target right now.
Don't worry about diving too deep into
the tooling because it's just changing.
But learn how to use them. learn how to
get value out of them because again
you're looking to provide value for your
employer. And so when you're, you know,
talking to a a person who's, you know,
interviewing you for a technical
interview, you can talk about the the AI
tooling and talk about what you know and
how you've worked with it and what
pitfalls you found as well as how you've
learned to work around those because
employers don't want to hear, "Oh, it's
great. I just tell what to do and it
just does it and does my job for me.
That's not what employers want to hear
because what they're what they're
hearing is you provide no value. But
instead, if you say this is what I found
and this is how I've I've learned to
optimize it. What you're saying is
here's how I drive the AI to make me
more efficient and effective while still
providing value. So learn how to do
that. So those are the supporting tools.
Let's talk about the supporting
languages because yes, when you learn a
language and I encourage you to learn C,
if that's your primary language, learn
it really well. Again, syntax is not
enough. Learn how to actually implement
it, learn how to build things with it.
But
after you do that to an extent, you're
going to have to learn other languages.
That's what developers do. And in fact,
someday maybe you'll find you're not
even developing C anymore. But while you
are, even still, you'll be learning more
languages than just C.
HTML and CSS, those are two, and you can
debate, you know, well, it's not a
programming language. It kind of is. Uh
either way, they're languages. Either
way, you need to know them more than
just I know how to do a div and I know
how to change the the font color.
You need to learn them a whole lot more
deeply than that. Learn them well with
that JavaScript. And here's a pitfall
that a lot of people jump into. They
say, "I haven't learned JavaScript, but
I use Angular."
Don't do that. Learn JavaScript first.
Vanilla JavaScript, meaning just
JavaScript, not a framework. Learn
JavaScript because those frameworks
change all the time and they're built on
a foundation of JavaScript. So when you
know JavaScript, know how it works, you
know what hoisting is, you know how um
it interacts with other things, you know
what let versus const versus var means,
you know these things and why they're
important, then you can make wise
choices around what you do. And this the
same thing is true if you're going to go
into TypeScript. That's fine. Great.
Typescript is can be great. But learn
JavaScript first so you know what it's
doing. Otherwise, what you end up with
is a a knowledge base that's full of
holes that you don't provide an
effective um query against your code to
go, hey, there's some problems here or
hey, let's there's a bug. You don't know
how to do that very well because of the
fact that you got a whole bunch of holes
in your knowledge. And again, what
you're gonna end up doing is letting the
AI lead and you're back to you're not
very valuable as a developer. So, learn
JavaScript. Well, TSQL
um learning this is kind of standin for
any uh database query language. Okay, if
you're using u MongoDB, there's a you
know MongoDB syntax. Whatever the syntax
is, learn how to use it. Well, so TSQL
is what we use for a lot of different
SQL engines, but um you know, Microsoft
SQL Server. Learn the TSQL. Learn more
than just the the select from um and
where query. Learn a lot deeper than
that. Learn how to effectively use TSQL
to optimize your query. Again, this is
where the performance of your
application is won or lost.
And finally, I'm putting this in here as
a as a language. Um, too often people
avoid the command line interface CLI.
Too often people will avoid it because
they say, "Well, that's just so old."
It's not. We talked earlier about
DevOps. Do you know what you're going to
have to do in DevOps? You're going to
have to perform a series of command line
arguments, a command line statements.
How do you know how to do that? by
knowing what the command line is and how
it works. Knowing the command line can
make you faster.
All every git tool is based upon the
command line. And too often what happens
is you'll get to use a git tool. It's
great and it works great, but this one
little edge case where you're like, oh,
it takes like five steps and you know,
doing things all over in order to do
this one thing. [snorts] And more often
than not, it's a oneliner in the command
line. And if you know that you can
supplement your your git guey with git
cli and just do the oneliner and done. I
have done this for years where I've I've
got a a git tool that I like and I use
for the most things but there's one
thing I just don't like and so I'll drop
down that CLI make that one command and
and back up I'm go. The same thing is
true for you know net. You can do almost
any net command as far as uh you know
creating new files or adding new
projects or linking things together,
adding uh packages and so on. You can do
all those things with the command line
that can be much faster. But also having
those skills allows you better at
DevOps. It allows you better at
automation. And so again it helps you
stand out from your peers. Okay. So
those are the kind of the the the goals
things to things to um learn and know.
Let's talk now about your career. Your
career is important and managing your
career is very important. So first of
all key characteristics
you need to be broadly knowledgeable.
Okay. So as a developer, yes, you should
be deeply knowledgeable about C if
you're a C# developer, but you also need
to be broadly knowledgeable. You should
be able to understand what's going on in
the industry around us, you should
understand what is a container and how
does it work. Even if you don't use it
every day, even if you don't use it at
all, you should know what it is and why
it's valuable. At least at that level,
be broadly knowledgeable. So you have a
conversation and B and able to say you
know what I don't use this but I
understand that you know this is
valuable for this and so I don't do that
area of things but you know if I were
going to this is what I would do. Uh
number two be skilled at identifying
flaws and AI suggestions. If you work
with the AI and it builds something and
if you can't find a flaw, the flaw is
probably you're not yet skilled enough
to work with the AI because the AI is
almost always inserting little flaws or
inserting little problems. The big one
here is that when you're working with
any size codebase at all, it's not going
to take the larger picture in mind. It
just can't. it doesn't have enough
tokens to put the entire application in
its memory, which means it's going to
not realize that certain methods aren't
there, or it's going to hallucinate that
certain methods are there. Um, or it's
not going to follow the same patterns as
the rest of your application, or it's
going to miss certain things. You need
to be able to evaluate that and identify
those flaws. And as those flaws get
bigger, you need to make sure that you
identify those because too many
applications that I've seen launched
recently have had major security
problems that make your application
vulnerable and by extension anyone who
is a client of your application. Every
one of your customers becomes vulnerable
and that can be business killing. So you
need to be absolutely certain you
understand how to identify flaws in any
AI suggestion you take or you shouldn't
use AI. Number three, you should be
aware of the big picture. When you're
working on an application, too often you
get heads down and focus on this one
little bug. You need to be able to pick
your head up and understand the big
picture because when you do, you can
make better decisions about what the
right choice is for that particular
situation. Because maybe you can make a
a simple change here that does this and
that's fine in the context of just that
little bit. But if you look at the
bigger picture, you realize that doesn't
serve the overall. And by being better
at being big picture aware, you can be
better in meetings when you're talking
to your boss and say, "Hey, that sounds
great, but here's why it's going to
impact something else over there." And
you become more of a leader in software
development,
be hardworking.
When an employer is thinking about their
best employees, they don't think of the
employees that slack off. They don't
think, you know what, I want more of
those people.
What they think is that that that Jill,
she works really hard. I like that. Even
if she punches in at 8:00 and punches
out at 5:00, she works really hard when
she's here. You know what? Be that
person. Show off that you can be that
person because that's what an employer
is going to value. Even if they don't
say it, even if it feels like they are
not paying attention to you, still be
hardwork. it will pay off. And then
don't be a whiner. Okay? Um, too often I
see people that are just complainers.
You know, they complain to their boss,
they complain to their co-workers, they
complain about the problems and all the
rest. Guess what? That doesn't leave a
good taste in anybody's mouth. When you
think about, hey, you know what? We've
got layoffs coming off coming soon and
we're going to have to lay off half the
people. Who do you think is getting laid
off? the person who is whining all the
time, the person is a hard worker. And
yes, there's more that goes into that
decision, but if it comes down to that,
you want to be a person that's
hardworking. You want to be a person
that is just known for being a
complainer because a complainer takes
energy away.
Don't just take energy away. Put energy
into everyone around you. Okay, let's
talk about an improvement plan. Uh,
number one, solve a real problem with an
application. So, if you're looking to
improve your career, number one, solve a
real problem with an application.
Find some problem that you have and
solve it. Okay? There are so many
problems. I have people tell me all the
time, "Oh, I I can't figure out a
problem." Maybe you're not building
enough applications. Maybe you're not,
you know, working enough with with
software development. Because the more
you start working with software
development, the more you start actually
building real things and the more you
start, you know, working through
training and all the rest, you're going
to find things. Maybe it's just you
figure out a way to track your training.
Maybe it is that you you find a flaw in
something that you don't like and you do
something better. Okay. Um, I did a
video not that long ago about how um I
built a a little this image viewer
because I found that there wasn't good
solutions out there that fit exactly
what I needed. I solved the real
problem. Wasn't a big problem, but I
solved the real problem and that made me
faster at doing my recording and doing
and doing this work. Well, guess what?
If I had a boss looking over my
shoulder, I could show them that and
say, "Hey, this is what I built." And it
saves me a few minutes every time I I do
a video, that can be of value.
Attend a meetup. Software developers
tend to be introverted. They tend to
focus on, hey, you know, I I don't want
to talk to people. I want to just put my
head down. Don't do that. Attend a
meetup. Meet other developers. You will
find that it puts your career forward
just by meeting other people because
you'll start talking about what you're
doing and what they're doing and you
will learn new things and you will you
will just grow by talking to others and
getting an outside perspective and and
seeing how they do things. So just that
alone will be of value. But then if you
do need a job, you have a network of
people that are working as developers
who would know of any openings for jobs.
And you'll have someone that can say,
"Hey, I know Tim and he's a developer."
And, you know, pass that on to their
boss. All of a sudden, you've bypassed
round one of the interview process. You
still have to go through the rest of the
rounds, but you've at least gotten a leg
up against all the rest of your
competition. you have stood out from the
crowd. So attend a meetup. It's also
just good for your career because you're
going to start learning and growing in
just what you're learning in that meetup
as well. So please do that. Also keep
your resume current. Keep working on how
many years experience do you have? What
skills have you learned? What things
should drop off your resume? And keep
that master resume that that main resume
that you have fresh with all the
information. Remember, you're going to
customize that resumeé to just the
important bits for any given
application, any given uh job
application, but you want to have that
that main resume up to date at all
times. It's just you're ready to go. It
also helps you go, I haven't really done
anything recently. And that's your kind
of kick in the pants and go do
something.
Add three new skills. Add three new
skills to your list of skills and things
that you know about. You don't have to
go in depth yet, but learn three new
things. Push yourself to go beyond just
what you do at your day job. Expand your
abilities
and then experiment.
So, experiment with new things, try new
things, figure out what works and what
doesn't work. work on an improvement
plan so that you are improving as a
developer and you are learning what you
like, what you don't like, what works,
what doesn't work. So even if you didn't
add a new skill to your resume, but you
try it out, you can have a conversation
about that. Say, you know what? I tried
that out. It just didn't work for me.
Here's why. And have that conversation.
Okay. Next up, the bottom line. So,
here's the bottom line for this whole
video, and that is that software
development is changing. You need to be
able to be more than just a prompt
engineer to get and maintain a job. It's
going to take work. It's going to take
effort on your part to get your job, to
maintain your job, to be better at your
job, but it's worth it. This career,
this field is awesome. And if you like
being in here, then you're going to need
to have put the work in to stay here.
But it's going to pay off. It's going to
be rewarding. So follow this. I hope you
have a great 2026. Dive in and make this
the best year ever for your software
development career.
[music]
>> [music]